Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates; Records apap057
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates Records
1979-1984
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap057
5.05 cubic ft.
Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates (CCAC) was organized as an informal group opposed to the construction of the Pyramid Crossgates mall in the summer of 1979.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Lindsay Childs.
Administrative History
Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates (CCAC) was organized as an informal group opposed to the construction of the Pyramid Crossgates mall in the summer of 1979. The group developed into a coalition of concerned residents that at one time had over three thousand members from the Town of Guilderland and neighboring communitites. Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates sought to preserve the rural and residential character of their town.
The administration of CCAC consisted of President Rhonda Childs, Treasurer Mary circa Phillips, and a Board of Directors which included the following members: Gregory R. Bell, Margaret McKinley, Donald J. Reeb, Drew Hartyell, and Anita Kershaw. Rhonda Childs and Mary circa Phillips continued as President and Treasurer until CCAC disbanded in 1984 when Crossgates was under construction.
CCAC was involved in hearings and suits against the Town of Guilderland Zoning, Planning, and Conservation Advisory Boards from 1979 to 1983. They initiated a lawsuit on September 18, 1981 against Robert F. Flacke, commissioner of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, the Town of Guilderland Zoning Appeals Board, the Albany County Planning Board, and David Axelrod, M.D., Commissioner of the New York State Department of Health, to overturn the decision made by the Water Merger Vote of August 27, 1980. CCAC was concerned that the construction of Crossgates would lead to a violation of Department of Health regulations protecting the watershed of McKownville.
CCAC was also involved as an intervenor in the 1981 Pyramid application for a special use permit for traffic and parking relief in the Town of Guilderland. From 1979 to 1982, CCAC was involved in a series of suits against Robert F. Flacke, individually and as Commissioner of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation. Two of the attorneys that represented CCAC during the lawsuits are Joel H. Sachs, of Plunkett and Jaffe, P.C., and George A. Rowland.
[1] Legal Papers. Water Merger: CCAC suit appealing Water Merger Vote, 1979, 1981-1982.
[2] Legal Papers. CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, Volume 1, 1982.
Scope and Contents
The records of Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates include subject files, legal papers, exhibits for hearings before the Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC), and News Clippings. Due to the informal nature of CCAC, the collection does not contain meeting minutes or correspondence of leaders in the organization, that would indicate the development of strategy.
CCAC's campaign against Crossgates Mall is documented by fliers, ads, election material, speeches, and legal documents supporting the suits that CCAC filed against the Town of Guilderland, Department of Environmental Conservation, and Robert F. Flacke. Other documents include permits, briefs, decisions, attorneys' correspondence, hearing submissions, and related material.
Several collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives provide further information about the construction of Crossgates Mall including the Crossgates Regional Shopping Mall Collection (APAP-067) and the records of Save the Pine Bush (APAP-125). A complete list of related collections is available at the subject guide for Conservation and the Environment.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1: Subject Files, 1969, 1971, 1974-1983, 1985-1986.
Series 2: Legal Papers, 1964, 1972, 1974, 1977-1983.
Series 3: DEC Exhibits, 1973, 1979-1980.
Series 4: News Clippings, 1975, 1977-1985, 1987.
Series 1 and 2 are arranged alphabetically; series 3 is arranged by exhibit number; series 4 is arranged chronologically.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Shopping malls; Urban development; Albany (N.Y.); Civil actions; Case files; Newspaper clippings; Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates; Crossgates Mall
- Subject Files, 1969; 1971; 1974-1983; 1985-1986; 1; 1.5 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence generated or received by Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates, petitions, fliers and ads relating to CCAC meetings, lists of CCAC speaking engagements and witnesses for CCAC. Also included are folders on the canidates for the 1980 Town of Guilderland elections. This series also contains data gathered on traffic at other malls and literature relating to residential property values.
  - CCAC Correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - CCAC Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - CCAC Correspondence, Legal, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - CCAC Correspondence, Legal, 1979-1982 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - CCAC Correspondence, Legal, 1981-1983 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - CCAC Correspondence concerning water permit, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - CCAC Correspondence from the town people, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - CCAC "Stop X Gate" Button., Undated (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Crossgates: Cartoon, ca. 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Crossgates: Effect on existing malls, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Crossgates: Grand opening of Jordan Marsh and Filene's, 1985 July 25 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Crossgates: Magazines, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Environmental Information, 1974; 1978-1981 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - Environmental Conservation Commissioner, Peter Berle, Resignation, 1978; 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Fliers, ads, etc. of CCAC, 1979-1982 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - Fliers, ads, etc. of CCAC, 1979-1983 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - Gary Nelson, Planning and Management consultant, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - Guilderland Democratic Party, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Industrial Development Agency papers, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Laws and regulations, 1978 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Letters from the public to CCAC regarding Crossgates, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Malls: Construction photographs, ca. 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Malls: General discussions, 1980-1982 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Malls: Public policy, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - McKownville becoming a village, Ideas, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Noise pollution and Danny Driscoll, 1978; 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - Petitions from people opposed to Crossgates, 1979 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - Pro-mall letters to CCAC, 1979-1981 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - Property valuation studies and correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Public hearing information of CCAC, 1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - Pyramid Company, Background information, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 31)
  - Real Property Tax, Exemptions, 1976; 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 32)
  - Residential property values, literature, 1977-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 33)
  - Speeches and appearances of CCAC, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 34)
  - Stores interested in Crossgates, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 35)
  - Suburban Growth Theory, 1980; 1983; 1986 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 36)
  - Traffic data on other malls, 1977; 1979-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 37)
  - Traffic references, 1971; 1978-1980 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 38)
  - Town of Guilderland Election materials, 1979; 1980; 1981 (Box 1 (1-Subject Files), Folder 39)
  - Town of Guilderland Election: Anne Gafney, 1980 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Town of Guilderland Election: Gordon Cannon, 1980 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Town of Guilderland Election: John Shea, 1980 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Town of Guilderland Election: Lindsy Childs, 1980 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Town of Guilderland Master Plan, 1969; 1975; 1980-1982 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Town of Guilderland related papers, 1979-1981 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - Town of Guilderland: Testimony of Margaret McKinley, 1978; 1980 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Town of Guilderland: Town Board meetings and correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Town of Guilderland: Traffic Data, 1981 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - V. Zappala & Co. v. Pyramid Co., 1981 and Interstate Properties v. Pyramid Co. (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Witnesses for CCAC., 1979-1980 (Box 2 (1-Subject Files), Folder 11)
- Legal Papers, 1964; 1972; 1974; 1977-1983; 2; 1.75 cubic ft.
  This series includes copies of Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC) commissioned studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment, society, and wildlife. This series also contains draft environmental impact statements, documentation for water merger appeals, and copies of Zoning Board records. Included in this series are 14 folders of maps that show plans for improvements on the mall site and surrounding area. There are nine folders containing documentation of CCAC suits against Robert F. Flacke.
  - DEC Air Quality Analysis (DOT), 1982 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 12)
  - DEC Applicant's response to 11/28/80 DEC decision, 1981 February 9 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 13)
  - DEC Briefs, Applications of Pyramid Crossgates Company, 1980 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 14)
  - DEC Briefs, decisions, post-decision and correspondence, 1980 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 15)
  - DEC Correspondence and final decision, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 16)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation, actual permits, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 17)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation cases pertaining to other malls, 1979; 1980; 1982 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 18)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation, final submissions, 1981-1982 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 19)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation Law, reform of part 621, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 20)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation Law, reform of part 624, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 21)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation Law, briefs and correspondence, 1981 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 22)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation notices, 1979-1980 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 23)
  - DEC Hearing submissions related to testimony before DEC, 1979-1980 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 24)
  - DEC Interrogatories, 1980 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 25)
  - DEC Reply briefs in regard to application of Pyramid Co., DEC case 401-09-S002, 1980 September 28 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 26)
  - DEC Subpoenas of DEC officials during hearings, 1980 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 27)
  - DEC Summary of Facts submitted by Pyramid Co. to Judge Dickerson in connection with applications for permits from DEC, 1980 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 28)
  - Maps: Layout Plan, 1979 May 30 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 29)
  - Maps: Profiles (of detention ponds), 1979 May 30 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 30)
  - Maps: Drainage Area Map-before development, 1979 May 30 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 31)
  - Maps: Plan and Profile, 1979 June 12 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 32)
  - Maps: U.S. Route 20-Highway Improvement Plan, 1979 October 16 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 33)
  - Maps: Washington Ave. Extension and Fuller road I-90 ramps, Highway Improvement Plan, 1979 October 17 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 34)
  - Maps: Utilities Plan, 1979 October 17 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 35)
  - Maps: Air Quality Data Plan, 1979 October 17 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 36)
  - Maps: Drainage Area Map--after development, 1979 October 17 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 37)
  - Maps: Highway Maintenance and Jurisdiction Plan, Alternative 4, 1979 November 08 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 38)
  - Maps: U.S. Route 20--Highway Improvement Plan, 1981 July 07 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 39)
  - Maps: U.S. Route 20--Highway Improvement Plan, 1981 July 17 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 40)
  - Maps: Highway Maintenance and Jurisdiction Plan, 1979 November 08 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 41)
  - Maps: Town of Guilderland, 1981 March 05 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 42)
  - Environment: Draft Environmental Impact statement, 1979 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 43)
  - Environment: Environmental Assessment Form (EAF), Pyramid Co. application, Part 1, 1979 May 30 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 44)
  - Environment: Draft Environmental statement, incomplete, 1979-1980 (Box 2 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 45)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment--air (Part l), 1978-1980 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 1)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment--air (Part ll), 1978-1980 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 2)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment-air (Part lll), 1978-1980 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 3)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment--society, 1979 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 4)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment--wildlife, 1979 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 5)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the traffic, 1980 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 6)
  - Studies on the impact of the economy, 1977 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 7)
  - Water Merger information, 1964; 1974; 1978; 1980 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 8)
  - Water Merger vote, 1980 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 9)
  - Water Merger: CCAC suit appealing water merger vote, 1972; 1980-1982 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 10)
  - Water Merger: CCAC suit appealing water merger vote, 1979; 1981-1982 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 11)
  - Water Merger: Suit appealing water merger vote, 1980 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 12)
  - Water Merger: Suit appealing water merger vote, 1980 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 13)
  - Water Merger: Suit appealing water merger vote, 1982-1983 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 14)
  - Zoning Board of Appeals, CCAC correspondence, 1981 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 15)
  - Zoning Board of Appeals, correspondence, 1981 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 16)
  - Zoning Board of Appeals, minutes of proceeding, 1981 September 09 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 17)
  - Zoning Board: Pyramid's applications before the Zoning Board, 1981 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 18)
  - Zoning Board: Susan Foster, concerning special permit for zoning, 1981 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 19)
  - Zoning Board: Albany Co. Planning Board, zoning and subdivision reviews and correspondence, 1981 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 20)
  - Zoning Board: CCAC v. Guilderland about rezoning, 1980; 1981-1982 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 21)
  - Zoning Board: CCAC suit against Town of Guilderland Zoning Board, 1980-1982 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 22)
  - Zoning Board of Appeals suit, Pyramid v. ZBA, October and November, 1981 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 23)
  - Zoning Board papers, suit, 1980-1982 (Box 3 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 24)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke and William J. Dickerson, Supreme Court, 1979-1980 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 1)
  - CCAC suit against Robert F. Flacke, DEC, 1981 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 2)
  - CCAC suit against Robert F. Flacke, Supreme Court, 1980-1981 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 3)
  - CCAC suit against Robert F. Flacke, Supreme Court, 1981 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 4)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, Supreme Court decision, 1982 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 5)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, Appelate, 1980-1982 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 6)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, Court of Appeals, 1982 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 7)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, volume 1, 1982 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 8)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, volume 2, 1982 (Box 4 (2-Legal Papers), Folder 9)
- DEC Exhibits, 1973; 1979-1980; 3; 1.0 cubic ft.
  Arranged by exhibit number.
  This series contains exhibits presented at DEC hearings from 1979-80. Included in this series are letters, surveys, reports, photographs, maps, and resumes of expert witnesses. The first folder contains a list of all exhibits.
  - List of exhibits, 1-333b, 1979 August 13-1980 July 24 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 1)
  - Exhibits #1-29, 1979-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 2)
  - Exhibits #30-52, 1978; 1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 3)
  - Exhibits #55-79, 1979-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 4)
  - Exhibits #80-99., Undated (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 5)
  - Exhibits #100-119, 1978-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 6)
  - Exhibits #120-139, 1978; 1979-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 7)
  - Exhibits #140-159, 1973; 1979-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 8)
  - Exhibits #160-179, 1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 9)
  - Exhibits #180-199, 1978; 1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 10)
  - Exhibits #200-219, Undated (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 11)
  - Exhibits #220-239, 1978-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 12)
  - Exhibits #240-259, 1978-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 13)
  - Exhibits #260-279, 1960-1977; 1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 14)
  - Exhibits #280-299, 1979-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 15)
  - Exhibits #300-333b., 1973; 1978-1980 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 16)
  - Service list; and possible list of CCAC members., 1980 July 14 (Box 4 (3-DEC Exhibits), Folder 17)
- News Clippings, 1975; 1977-1985; 1987; 4; 0.8 cubic ft.
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains copies and originals of News Clippings primarily from the Albany Times Union and Schenectady Gazette.
  - News Clippings, 1975 (Box 5 (4-News Clippings), Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, 1977 (Box 5 (4-News Clippings), Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1978 (Box 5 (4-News Clippings), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1979 (Box 5 (4-News Clippings), Folder 4-5)
  - News Clippings, 1980 (Box 5 (4-News Clippings), Folder 6-10)
  - News Clippings, 1981 (Box 6 (4-News Clippings), Folder 1-2)
  - News Clippings, 1982 (Box 6 (4-News Clippings), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1983 (Box 6 (4-News Clippings), Folder 4)
  - News Clippings, 1984 (Box 6 (4-News Clippings), Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, 1985 (Box 6 (4-News Clippings), Folder 6)
  - News Clippings, 1987 (Box 6 (4-News Clippings), Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, Undated (Box 6 (4-News Clippings), Folder 8)
  - Pine Bush, News Clippings, 1977-1981 (Box 6 (4-News Clippings), Folder 9)